In the spring of 2016,
في ربيع سنة 2016،
a legal battle between Apple and the Federal Bureau of Investigation
معركة قانونية بين شركة أبل ومكتب التحقيقات الفيدرالي
captured the world's attention.
لفتت انتباه العالم.
Apple has built security features into its mobile products
ضمت شركة أبل خصائص أمنية لمنتجاتها المحمولة
which protect data on its devices from everyone but the owner.
تحمي البيانات على أجهزتها من الجميع ماعدا مالك الجهاز
That means that criminals, hackers and yes, even governments
وذلك يعني بأن المجرمين والهاكرز وأيضًا حتى الحكومة
are all locked out.
لا يمكنها الولوج للبيانات.
For Apple's customers, this is a great thing.
بالنسبة لمستخدمين أبل، ذلك شيء عظيم.
But governments are not so happy.
لكن الحكومات ليست سعيدة بهذا الشأن.
You see, Apple has made a conscious decision
قامت أبل باتخاد قرارٍ واعٍ
to get out of the surveillance business.
لتخرج من الأعمال الرقابية.
Apple has tried to make surveillance as difficult as possible
حاولت أبل أن تجعل المراقبة أمرًا عسيرًا
for governments and any other actors.
بالنسبة للحكومات وسائر الأطراف الأخرى.
There are really two smartphone operating systems
يوجد في الواقع نظامين تشغيليين للهواتف الذكية
in the global smartphone market:
في السوق العالمية للهواتف الذكية:
iOS and Android.
آي أو أس IOS وأندرويد Android.
iOS is made by Apple. Android is made by Google.
آي أو أس مصنّع من قبل أبل وأندرويد مصنّع من قبل غوغل.
Apple has spent a lot of time and money
صرفت شركة أبل الكثير من الوقت والمال
to make sure that its products are as secure as possible.
للتأكد من أن منتجاتها آمنة قدر الإمكان.
Apple encrypts all data stored on iPhones by default,
تشفر أبل تلقائيًا جميع البيانات المخزنة في أجهزة الأيفون،
and text messages sent from one Apple customer to another Apple customer
والرسائل النصية التي تُرسل من مستخدم أبل إلى مستخدم أبل آخر
are encrypted by default
مشفره تلقائيًا
without the user having to take any actions.
من دون أن يتخذ المستخدم أية إجراءات لذلك.
What this means is that,
ما يعنيه ذلك هو أنه
if the police seize an iPhone and it has a password,
عندما تصادر الشرطة جهاز iPhone يمتلك كلمة مرور،
they'll have a difficult time getting any data off of it,
سيكون من الصعوبة عليهم الحصول على أي بيانات من الجهاز،
if they can do it at all.
إن كان بإمكانهم ذلك.
In contrast, the security of Android just really isn't as good.
في المقابل، مستوى الأمن للأندرويد ليس جيد بما فيه الكفاية.
Android phones, or at least most of the Android phones
أجهزة أندرويد، أو على الأقل معظم أجهزة أندرويد
that have been sold to consumers,
التي تم بيعها للزبائن،
do not encrypt data stored on the device by default,
لا تشفر البيانات المخزنة عليها تلقائيًا،
and the built-in text messaging app in Android does not use encryption.
وتطبيق الرسائل النصية المدمج بها لا يستخدم التشفير.
So if the police seize an Android phone,
لذلك عندما تصادر الشركة جهاز أندرويد،
chances are, they'll be able to get all the data they want
الاحتمالات بأنها ستكون قادرة على الحصول على كافة البيانات التي تريدها
off of that device.
من ذلك الجهاز.
Two smartphones
جهازان ذكيّان
from two of the biggest companies in the world;
من اثنتين من أكبر الشركات في العالم
one that protects data by default,
جهاز يحمي البيانات تلقائيًا،
and one that doesn't.
والآخر لا يفعل ذلك.
Apple is a seller of luxury goods.
تعتبر شركة أبل بائعة للسلع الفاخرة.
It dominates the high end of the market.
وتسيطر على سوق المنتجات الراقية.
And we would expect a manufacturer of luxury goods to have products
لذلك نتوقع من مصنّع للسلع الفاخرة أن تكون منتجاته
that include more features.
شاملة للمزيد من المميزات.
But not everyone can afford an iPhone.
ولكن ليس الجميع قادر على تحمل تكلفة الـ iPhone
That's where Android really, really dominates:
هنا حيث يسيطر الأندرويد تمامًا
at the middle and low end of the market,
للمنتجات متوسطة ومنخفضة التكلفة من السوق،
smartphones for the billion and a half people
هواتف ذكية لمليار ونصف من الناس
who cannot or will not spend
الذين لا يستطيعون أو لا يريدون إنفاق
600 dollars on a phone.
600 دولار على هاتف.
But the dominance of Android has led to what I call
ولكن سيطرة الأندرويد أدت إلى ما أسميه
the "digital security divide."
"انقسام الأمن الرقمي"
That is, there is now increasingly a gap
هنالك الآن فجوة متزايدة
between the privacy and security of the rich,
بين الخصوصية والأمن للأغنياء،
who can afford devices that secure their data by default,
الذين باستطاعتهم تحمّل تكلفة أجهزة تحمي بياناتهم تلقائيًا،
and of the poor,
والفقراء
whose devices do very little to protect them by default.
التي تفعل أجهزتهم القليل جدًا لحماية بياناتهم بشكل تلقائي.
So, think of the average Apple customer:
لذلك بالنسبة لمتوسط مستخدمي أبل:
a banker, a lawyer, a doctor, a politician.
المصرفي، المحامي، الطبيب، السياسي
These individuals now increasingly have smartphones in their pockets
هؤلاء الأفراد وعلى نحو متزايد أصبحوا يمتلكون هواتف ذكية في جيوبهم
that encrypt their calls, their text messages,
تشفّر مكالماتهم ورسائلهم النصية،
all the data on the device,
وكل البيانات في الجهاز،
without them doing really anything to secure their information.
دون أي مجهود منهم لتأمين بياناتهم
In contrast, the poor and the most vulnerable in our societies
في المقابل، الفقراء والفئات الأكثر ضعفًا في مجتمعاتنا
are using devices that leave them completely vulnerable to surveillance.
يستخدمون أجهزة تتركهم عرضة تمامًا للمراقبة.
In the United States, where I live,
في الولايات المتحدة، حيث أعيش،
African-Americans are more likely to be seen as suspicious
الأمريكيون من أصل أفريقي معرّضين أكثر لأن ينظر لهم على أنهم مشبوهين
or more likely to be profiled,
أو من المحتمل أن يكون لديهم سجل،
and are more likely to be targeted by the state with surveillance.
وهم أكثر عرضة للاستهداف من قبل الدولة عن طريق المراقبة.
But African-Americans are also disproportionately likely
ولكن الأمريكيين من أصل أفريقي من المحتمل وبشكل غير متناسب
to use Android devices that do nothing at all
أن يستخدموا أجهزة أندرويد التي لا تفعل شيئًا على الإطلاق
to protect them from that surveillance.
لحمايتهم من تلك المراقبة.
This is a problem.
هذه معضلة.
We must remember that surveillance is a tool.
علينا أن نتذكر بأن المراقبة هي أداة.
It's a tool used by those in power
أداة تستخدم من قبل من لديهم سلطة
against those who have no power.
ضد أولئك الذين ليست لديهم تلك السلطة.
And while I think it's absolutely great
بينما أفكر بأنه لشيء عظيم
that companies like Apple are making it easy for people to encrypt,
أن شركات مثل أبل تجعل من السهل على الناس التشفير،
if the only people who can protect themselves
إذا كان الوحيدين الذين يحمون أنفسهم
from the gaze of the government
من رقابة الحكومة
are the rich and powerful,
هم الأغنياء وأصحاب السلطة،
that's a problem.
تلك مشكلة.
And it's not just a privacy or a cybersecurity problem.
وإنها ليست مجرد خصوصية أو مشكلة أمنية.
It's a civil rights problem.
إنها مشكلة حقوق مدنية.
So the lack of default security in Android
لذا فإن نقص الأمن الافتراضي في الأندرويد
is not just a problem for the poor and vulnerable users
ليس مشكلة فقط للمستخدمين الفقراء والفئات الأكثر ضعفًا
who are depending on these devices.
التي تعتمد على تلك الأجهزة.
This is actually a problem for our democracy.
في الواقع تلك مشكلة لديموقراطيتنا
I'll explain what I mean.
سأوضح ما أعنيه.
Modern social movements rely on technology --
تعتمد الحركات الاجتماعية الحديثة على التكنولوجيا
from Black Lives Matter to the Arab Spring to Occupy Wall Street.
من "حياة السود مهمة" إلى "الربيع العربي" إلى "احتلوا وول ستريت".
The organizers of these movements and the members of these movements
المنظمين لتلك الحركات وأعضاء تلك الحركات
increasingly communicate and coordinate with smartphones.
يتواصلون بتزايد وينسقون عن طريق الأجهزة الذكية.
And so, naturally governments that feel threatened by these movements
لذلك وبطبيعة الحال الحكومات التي تشعر بأنها مهددة من قبل تلك الحركات
will also target the organizers and their smartphones.
ستستهدف المنظمين وأجهزتهم الذكية.
Now, it's quite possible
الآن ومن الممكن جداً
that a future Martin Luther King or a Mandela or a Gandhi
بأن مارتن لوثر كنج أو مانديلا أو غاندي المستقبليين
will have an iPhone and be protected from government surveillance.
سيكون لديهم أيفون محمي من مراقبة الحكومة.
But chances are,
ولكن هنالك احتمالات
they'll probably have a cheap, $20 Android phone in their pocket.
قد يكون لديهم هاتف أندرويد رخيص بقيمة 20 دولار في جيوبهم.
And so if we do nothing to address the digital security divide,
ولذلك إن لم نفعل شيء لمعالجة انقسام الأمن الرقمي،
if we do nothing to ensure that everyone in our society
وإن لم نفعل شيء للتأكد من أن كل فرد في مجتمعنا
gets the same benefits of encryption
يحصل على نفس الفوائد من التشفير
and is equally able to protect themselves from surveillance by the state,
وأن يكون الجميع بالتساوي قادرين على حماية أنفسهم من رقابة الدولة،
not only will the poor and vulnerable be exposed to surveillance,
وليس فقط الفقراء والفئات الضعيفة من تكون معرضة للمراقبة،
but future civil rights movements may be crushed
لكن بالمستقبل قد يتم قمع حركات الحقوق المدنية
before they ever reach their full potential.
قبل أن تصل لكامل إمكاناتها.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Helen Walters: Chris, thank you so much.
هيلين والترز: كريس، شكرًا جزيلاً لك.
I have a question for you.
لدي سؤال لك.
We saw recently in the press
شاهدنا مؤخرًا بالإعلام
that Mark Zuckerberg from Facebook covers over his camera
بأن مارك زاكيربيرغ من الفيس بوك يغطي كاميرته
and does something with his headphone mic jack.
ويفعل شيئاً بسماعته.
So I wanted to ask you a personal question, which is:
لذا أود أن اسألك سؤالاً شخصيًا هو:
Do you do that?
هل تفعل ذلك؟
And, on behalf of everyone here, particularly myself,
وبالنيابة عن الجميع هنا، وخاصة أنا شخصيًا،
Should we be doing that?
هل من الواجب علينا فعل ذلك؟
Should we be covering these things?
هل يجب علينا تغطية هذه الأشياء؟
Christopher Soghoian: Putting a sticker -- actually, I like Band-Aids,
- وضع ملصق، في الواقع أنا أميل لذلك،
because you can remove them and put them back on
لأنك يمكنك إزالتها ووضعها مرة أخرى
whenever you want to make a call or a Skype call.
عندما تريد إجراء مكالمة أو مكالمة سكايبي.
Putting a sticker over your web cam
وضع ملصق على الكاميرا
is probably the best thing you can do for your privacy
ربما يكون أفضل عمل بإمكانك فعله لخصوصيتك
in terms of bang for buck.
من ناحية التنفيذ وتوفير المال.
There really is malware, malicious software out there
هنالك فعلاً برامج ضارة وبرمجيات خبيثة
that can take over your web cam,
التي بإمكانها فتح كاميرتك،
even without the light turning on.
من دون تشغيل الضوء.
This is used by criminals. This is used by stalkers.
ويستخدم هذا من قبل المجرمين. ومن قبل الملاحقين
You can buy $19.99 "spy on your ex-girlfriend" software online.
بإمكانك شراء برنامج بـ 19.99 دولار "تجسس على صديقتك السابقة" من النت
It's really terrifying.
إنه حقًا مخيف.
And then, of course, it's used by governments.
وبالطبع يستخدم من قبل الحكومات
And there's obviously a sexual violence component to this,
وهنالك بالتأكيد عنصر العنف الجنسي إلى ذلك،
which is that this kind of surveillance can be used most effectively
حيث يستخدم هذا النوع من المراقبة بأكثر فعالية
against women and other people who can be shamed in our society.
ضد المرأة وغيرهم من الناس الذي يمكن فضحهم في مجتمعنا.
Even if you think you have nothing to hide,
حتى لو ظننت أنه لا يوجد لديك شيء لتخفيه
at the very least, if you have children, teenagers in your lives,
على أقل تقدير، إن كان لديك أطفال أو مراهقين في حياتك،
make sure you put a sticker on their camera and protect them.
تأكد من وضع ملصق على الكاميرا و قم بحمايتهم.
HW: Wow. Thank you so much. CS: Thank you.
- مذهل، شكرًا جزيلاً لك. - شكرًا
HW: Thanks, Chris.
- شكرًا، كريس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)